Finding Aid for Pittsfield Township records, 1830-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pittsfield Township records 1830-1980
Pittsfield Charter Township (Mich.)
86329 Cb.2/2; CB.2 Outsize
The Pittsfield Township (Washtenaw County, Mich.) records contain school district records for districts 1 through 8 and 8 fractional from 1860-1930, with occasional records dating back to 1830. The collection also contains a wide range of types of township records dealing with assessments, elections, finance, and legal activities, dating from 1832 to 1980. Township Board proceedings (1834-1965, with some gaps) and road records (1835-1887) are also available in digitized versions.
7 linear feet in 8 boxes
121 oversize volumes
1.98 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from different sources. Pittsfield School District No. 7 (also known as Stone School (donor no. 2981 ) deposited its records in 1953. Other records came from the township office (donor no. 4972 ) in 1972 through township treasurer James D. Reader. Finally a history of the township schools was received from Julius Haab (donor no. 1854 ) in 1943. Additional records came from the township office in 2010 and 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Pittsfield Township, created in 1834, was one of the earliest townships in Washtenaw County. The "History of the Rural Schools in Washtenaw County" found in the collection covers only Pittsfield Township. The history of each district was written by students. The entire history was given to the Michigan Historical Collection by Julius W. Haab. Miscellaneous school documents include the Centennial Celebration of Stone School in 1953.
The school records of Pittsfield are arranged generally by district.
District 1
District 1 fractional - Pittsfield and Saline
District 2 fractional - Pittsfield and York
District 2 and 5 fractional - Pittsfield and York
District 3
District 3 fractional - Pittsfield and Lodi
District 4 fractional - Pittsfield and Lodi
District 5
District 6
District 7
District 7 fractional - Pittsfield and York
District 8 fractional - Pittsfield and York
The collection consists of the following series: Pittsfield School Districts records, Miscellaneous Township Responsibilities, Township Administration, Treasurer's records, Assessment Rolls, Tax Rolls, Rolls of Lands Upon Which Taxes Were Unpaid, and Other Assessments.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Elections--Michigan--Pittsfield (Township); Roads--Michigan--Pittsfield (Township); Schools--Michigan--Pittsfield (Township); Stone School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Taxation--Michigan--Pittsfield (Township); Washtenaw County (Mich.); Pittsfield Charter Township (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Schools.; Parsons, Harriet G.; Photographs.; Pittsfield Charter Township (Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Stone School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Washtenaw County (Mich.); Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Pittsfield School Districts 1830-1980
  - Historical Background
    - History of the Rural Schools in Washtenaw County 1943 (Box 1)
    - Maps of Pittsfield Township 1838, 1861 (Box 1)
    - Stone School Centennial Celebration 1953 (Box 1)
      (with photographs)
    - Teachers of Washtenaw County 1879-1884 (Box 1)
  - Census and Annual Reports for Pittsfield School Districts
    - Unidentified forms, undated 1890, 1905, 1914 (Box 1)
    - District 1
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
    - District 1 fractional
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 2 fractional
      - Undated 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 2 and 5 fractional
      - Undated 1870-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 3
      - 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 3 fractional
      - Undated 1848, 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 4 and 8 undated, 1855-1909 (Box 1)
  - Census and Annual Reports for Pittsfield School Districts (cont.)
    - District 5
      - Undated 1839, 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 5 fractional 1860 (Box 1)
    - District 6
      - 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 7
      - 1850-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
      - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 7 fractional
      - Undated 1860-1869 (Box 1)
      - 1870-1879 (Box 1)
      - 1880-1889 (Box 1)
      - 1890-1899 (Box 1)
      - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
      - 1910-1929 (Box 1)
    - District 8 fractional 1855-1909 (Box 1)
  - School Registers
    - District 7 fractional, 10 volumes
      - 1877-1878 (Box 1)
      - 1878-1881 (Box 1)
      - 1881-1884 (Box 1)
      - 1884-1888 (Box 1)
      - 1889-1892 (Box 1)
      - 1892-1894 (Box 1)
      - 1894-1900 (Box 1)
      - 1902-1906 (Box 1)
      - 1906-1915 (Box 1)
      - 1915-1921 (Box 1)
  - School District 7 fractional
    - School District Record, 2 volumes
      - 1865-1894 (Box 2)
      - 1894-1903 (Box 2)
    - Minutes of Stone School P.T.A. 1921-1928 (Box 2)
    - Centennial History of District 7 fractional 1925 (Box 2)
  - Directors Reports
    - District 1 1850-1859 (Box 2)
    - District 1 fractional 1850-1859 (Box 2)
    - District 2
      - 1830-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 (Box 2)
    - District 2 and 5 fractional
      - 1840-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 1862 (Box 2)
    - District 3
      - 1840-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 1863 (Box 2)
    - District 3 fractional
      - 1837 1840-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 (Box 2)
    - District 4 1830-1840 (Box 2)
    - District 4 and 8 fractional
      - Undated 1839, 1840-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 1861 (Box 2)
    - District 5
      - Undated 1830-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 1862 (Box 2)
    - District 7
      - 1839 1840-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 1862 (Box 2)
    - District 7 fractional
      - 1839 1840-1849 (Box 2)
      - 1850-1859 (Box 2)
  - Inspectors Annual Reports
    - 1840-1849 (Box 2)
    - 1850-1859 (Box 2)
    - 1860-1869 (Box 2)
    - 1870-1879 (Box 2)
    - 1880-1889 (Box 2)
    - 1890-1899 (Box 2)
    - 1900-1909 (Box 2)
    - Petitions to School Inspectors undated, 1842-1860 (Box 2)
  - Township Clerk's Annual Reports
    - 1910-1919 (Box 2)
    - 1920-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930-1932 (Box 2)
  - Stone School
    - Albums of class pictures of students 1970s-1980s (Box 5)
  - Pittsfield Township Library
    - Librarians Reports 1849-1854 (Box 3)
    - Rules and Holdings undated, 1847-1849 (Box 3)
  - School District Finances
    - Apportionment of Primary School Monies from Michigan Department of Public Instruction 1901-1909 (Box 3)
    - Apportionment of Primary School Monies from County Treasurer 1845-1855, 1873, 1900-1909 (Box 3)
    - Township Treasurer's Reports concerning School Monies 1871, 1887, 1893-1894, 1903-1908 (Box 3)
    - School Monies
      - District 1 1870-1904 (Box 3)
      - District 1 fractional. 1880-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 2 and 5 fractional 1870-1909 (Box 3)
      - District 3 1870-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 3 fractional 1875, 1912-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 4 and 8 fractional 1880-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 5, undated 1875, 1880-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 6 1870-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 7 1870-1913 (Box 3)
      - District 7 fractional
        - 1870-1913 (Box 3)
        - Account Book 1910-1929, 1 volumes (Box 3)
        - Account book 1929-1934 (Box 3)
        - Account book 1935-1941 (Box 3)
    - Receipt book 1899-1908 (schools and teachers) (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Township Responsibilities 1832-1978
  - Highways
    - Road Record Book and Determinations 1835-1887, .ZIP file (Box 3)
    - Highway Tax Lists
      - District 7 and 8 undated, 1838 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous Districts 1840-1843 (Box 3)
      - District 1-26 1844 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous Districts 1845 (Box 3)
      - District 1-30 1847 (Box 3)
      - District 1-33 1848 (Box 3)
      - District 1-34 1849 (Box 3)
      - District 1-34 1850, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - District 1-34 1852 (Box 3)
      - District 1-33 1854 (Box 3)
    - Receipts of Highway Commissioners 1868, 1874-1878 (Box 3)
    - Highway Expenditures, undated 1844-1846, 1849, 1863 (Box 3)
    - Reports of Highway Commissioners 1835-1859 (Box 3)
    - Petitions to Highway Commissioners 1836, 1844-1847, 1860, 1875 (Box 3)
    - Surveys of Township Highways 1832-1847, 1850 (Box 3)
    - Contract for Highways 1839 (Box 3)
    - Appointments to position of Highway Overseer 1839, 1849 (Box 3)
  - Dog Lists
    - 1865-1869 (Box 3)
    - 1870-1872 (Box 3)
    - 1880 1883 (Box 3)
  - Marks and Brands 1834-1850 (Box 3)
    (also includes animal complaints)
  - Elections
    - Party Enrollment
      - 1906-1910, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      - 1912, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - Poll Lists
      - 1884 1886-1888 (Box 3)
      - 1904 (Box 3)
    - Poll Book
      - 1889 (Box 3)
      - 1893 (Box 3)
      - 1894 (Box 3)
      - 1898 (Box 3)
      - 1905 (Box 3)
      - 1912 (Box 3)
      - 1915 (Box 3)
    - Sheriff's Notices of Elections 1845-1849 (Box 3)
    - Tally Sheets
      - 1886, 1891, 1898 (Box 3)
      - 1896 of General Election (Box 3)
      - 1909 of General Election (Box 3)
      - 1913 of Primary Election (Box 3)
      - 1914 of General Primary Election (Box 3)
      - 1916 of General Primary Election (Box 3)
      - 1917 of General Primary Election (Box 3)
      - 1918 of General Primary Election (Box 3)
      - 1920 (Box 3)
    - Statement of Votes of Annual Township Meeting 1914 (Box 3)
    - Statement of Votes of General Primary Election 1915 (Box 3)
    - Statement of Votes of General Election and Annual Township Meeting 1915 (Box 3)
    - Canvass of votes cast 1957-1978 (Box 3)
    - Register of Men and Women Electors 1924-1932 (Volume 18)
- Township Administration 1834-1965
  - Proceedings of the Town Board meetings (proceedings of annual meetings, election results, officers, votes on ordinances, etc.)
    - 1834-1850, .ZIP file (Box 6)
    - 1850-1873, .ZIP file (Box 6)
    - 1924-1947, .ZIP file (Box 6)
    - 1947, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1948, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1949, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1950, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1951, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1952, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1953, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1954, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1955, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1956, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1957, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1958, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1959, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1960, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1961, .ZIP file (Box 7)
    - 1961-1963, .ZIP file (Box 8)
    - 1963-1965, .ZIP file (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous documents presented at township meeting 1835-1845 (Box 8)
  - Minutes of Pittsfield Township Board of Health 1857 (Box 8)
  - Officeholders of Pittsfield Township 1834-1974 (Box 8)
  - Bonds and oaths of office of township officials circa 1926-1955 (Box 8)
  - Jury Lists 1839-1910 (Box 8)
  - Miscellanea (Box 8)
  - Franchises 1869-1906 (Box 8)
  - Record book: recipients of welfare payments (Box 8)
- Treasurer's records and other financial 1839-1954
  - Building permit register 1948-1953 (Box 8)
  - Building permit register 1953-1958 (Box 8)
  - Building, heating and other permits 1959-1961 (Volume 1)
  - Financial Statements of Pittsfield Township 1898-1953 (Box 8)
  - Bonds 1839-1843 (Box 8)
  - Chattel Mortgages Entry Book 1847-1880, 1 volumes (Box 8)
  - Accounts against Pittsfield Township 1840 (Box 8)
  - Treasurer's Account Books
    - 1847-1861, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - 1855-1857, 1 volumes (Volume 2)
    - 1868-1882 (Box 8)
    - 1873-1885, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - 1881-1899, 1 volumes (Box 8)
    - 1900-1909 (Volume 3)
    - 1909-1914 (Volume 4)
    - 1915-1919 (Volume 5)
    - 1919-1927 (Volume 6)
    - 1927-1933 (Volume 7)
    - 1933-1936 (Volume 8)
    - 1936-1947 (Volume 9)
  - Clerk's Account Books
    - 1923-1933 (Volume 10)
      (include some later dated records)
    - 1933-1936 (Volume 11)
    - 1936-1947 (Volume 12)
  - Daybook of receipts and deposits 1953-1954 (Volume 13)
- Assessment Rolls
  - 1835-1872, 33 folders (Box 4)
    (some years missing)
  - 1873-1956, 61 volumes (Volume 4)
- Tax Rolls
  - 1952-1980, 42 volumes (Volume 5)
- Other Assessments
  - Statement of Lands Upon Which Taxes for the Year "" were Unpaid
    - 1948-1960 (Volume 14)
    - 1961-1963 1968 (Volume 15)
    - 1969-1971 (Volume 16)
      (the volume also contains fragmentary information for 1964-1968)
  - Special Assessment Sewer 1958 (Volume 17)